<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>The CIA D-class</title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2026-01-23T22:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>End of the Terror | Memory, Declassification, and the Legacy of Argentina&#x27;s &quot;Dirty War&quot;</title>
        <published>2026-01-23T22:30:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-23T22:30:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Brodin Faser
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/memory-and-legacy/"/>
        <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/memory-and-legacy/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/memory-and-legacy/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;end-of-the-terror-memory-declassification-and-the-legacy-of-argentina-s-dirty-war&quot;&gt;End of the Terror | Memory, Declassification, and the Legacy of Argentina&#x27;s &quot;Dirty War&quot;&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#end-of-the-terror-memory-declassification-and-the-legacy-of-argentina-s-dirty-war&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after the &quot;Dirty War&quot; ended, its effects can still be felt. The
remembrance of the atrocities committed is distorted by the United States&#x27;
sanitization. While the declassified CIA documents help shine light on the
events of the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; they also demonstrate the controlled narrative about
US involvement that was pushed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-article&quot;&gt;The Article&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#the-article&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is it! This is the last article in my series on the Argentinian &quot;Dirty
War.&quot; Throughout this series, we have outlined a clear pattern in the
relationship between the United States and Argentina. This pattern includes
inaction despite knowledge of an imminent coup d&#x27;état, the overarching Cold War
political atmosphere that prioritized ideological alignment over human rights,
and a narrative that sanitizes repression through euphemisms and silence.
However, the consequences of these decisions did not magically dissipate after
the collapse of the dictatorship in 1983. To this day, they shape our
understanding of the &quot;Dirty War&quot; and how it is remembered, both in Argentina as
well as in the United States.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memory is not a passive process. It weaves together narratives and events of
the past, the voices of those involved, and the material evidence of their
existence. In Argentina, the transition out of the dictatorship into a
democracy was accompanied by a focused effort to remember and acknowledge the
past. The creation of CONADEP (the National Commission on the Disappearance of
Persons) commemorates this attempt to acknowledge and document the period of
state terror. To ensure those that were persecuted are not forgotten, Nunca Mas
catalogued the forced disappearances, tortures, and extrajudicial murders in
1984, offering surviving family members&#x27; and friends&#x27; testimonials of these
individuals to counteract the years of denial and repression. This began the
reframing of the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; not as a legitimate persecution of
counterterrorist ideals in the name of national security, but as the systematic
persecution of a nation&#x27;s own people through structured violence and human
rights atrocities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, movements such as Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo challenge the
silence though public memory. By marching weekly and demanding information
about their disappeared children, they resisted the narrative imposed upon them
by the military regime and its attempts to erase their loved ones from history.
This highlights that memory does not rely upon consensus, but in the diversity
of courageous voices willing to speak out against the consensus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States however, the legacy of the &quot;Dirty War&quot; is presented
differently. For decades, US officials refused to acknowledge US involvement or
knowledge of the situation in Argentina, keeping it fragmented and inaccessible
to the public. While the CIA and other intelligence agencies suppressed the
information about the &quot;Dirty War&quot; in real time, the records of this
sanitization were kept hidden from the public eye. As a result, the public
memory of the &quot;Dirty War&quot; and its violence slipped through the cracks of
American responsibility and awareness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once these classified documents began to be released from the late 1990s into
the 2010s, this perception started to shift. Thousands of documents were
released, revealing the US involvement and permission of human rights
violations, forced disappearances, and acknowledgment of the military regime&#x27;s
justification for the repression. These released documents did not change what
the Argentinian survivors already knew, but it confirmed that the US willfully
ignored the situation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historians like Carlos Osorio have argued that declassification serves two
purposes: it enforces accountability while also exposing the limitations of
delayed transparency. Documents released decades after the event cannot prevent
atrocities, but it can give them context.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These records help demonstrate how narrative shapes memory. As shown through
the many articles given previously, US officials consistently describe the
Argentinian repression using sanitized and politically correct language, such
as countersubversion and stability control efforts. This kind of language
influences how historians and readers reflect on the past. Even when documents
acknowledge the torture and forced disappearances, the emotional toll of these
events is dampened by the professional tone. The CIA archive itself is where
the violence of Videla and the regime is simultaneously revealed and obscured.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues of censorship, sanitization, and silence extend beyond Argentina.
The &quot;Dirty War&quot; serves as a case study in the power of state-controlled
information over the public. By controlling the language used to communicate
the Argentinian situation, delaying the declassification and spread of this
information, and prioritizing the geopolitical agenda during the Cold War, the
United States shaped both the physical events that occurred and the historical
record of them afterward. In this framework, memory acts as an extension of US
policy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, memory is dynamic. There are ongoing trials of regime officials in
Argentina, revitalized public discussion, and continued discovery of archived
information that challenges this controlled narrative. Each document that is
disclosed to the public breaks the silence of those who suffered under the
military regime, forcing a reevaluation of the responsibility that the US held
in the &quot;Dirty War.&quot; In this way, the past remains fluid and ever changing,
refusing to slip into obscurity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this, the legacy of the &quot;Dirty War&quot; is not only one marred by terror and
desperate survival, but also of challenged remembrance. It consistently raises
questions for all powerful nations, namely the responsibility for action in the
face of known tyrannical behavior. Who is responsible for the tens of thousands
of lives extinguished during the authoritarian reign of Videla and his regime?
And how is this story preserved or suppressed through the narratives of the
public?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following the influence that the US had on the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; from
foreknowledge of the imminent coup to the Cold War justifications and narrative
control, this series argues that the United States was not merely a bystander
in Argentina&#x27;s struggle. They were willing to turn a blind eye to a nation
tumbling into chaos and immorality because it fit into their political
narrative and objectives. The memory and remembrance of this does not dismiss
the responsibility of the US; rather it exposes their complacency. The
lingering question is whether the acknowledgment of Argentina&#x27;s past will spur
accountability, or whether silence will once again triumph.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you all for joining me in this series. Until next time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>The American Narrative | Censorship, Sanitization, and Silence</title>
        <published>2026-01-23T22:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-23T22:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Brodin Faser
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/santization-and-censorship/"/>
        <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/santization-and-censorship/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/santization-and-censorship/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-american-narrative-censorship-sanitization-and-silence&quot;&gt;The American Narrative | Censorship, Sanitization, and Silence&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#the-american-narrative-censorship-sanitization-and-silence&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US intelligence heavily censored and sanitized the events of the &quot;Dirty War&quot;
within their own circles and to the general public. Because of this, the
atrocities committed in a faraway nation became tolerable. The public did not
know the full extent to which the Argentinian government was terrorizing its
own people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-article&quot;&gt;The Article&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#the-article&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous article, we looked at how Cold War ideologies and tensions
shaped the US&#x27; attitude towards Argentina&#x27;s &quot;Dirty War,&quot; framing the
Argentinian repression as a geopolitical struggle against communism rather than
a series of human rights violations. The US not only understood the logic
driving the military regime, but anticipated it. Despite this, the US decided
not to intervene. This refusal to intervene also shaped the way information
concerning the situation was communicated, both within the CIA as well as the
general American public. In other words, not only did the US refuse to
intervene, they also tightly controlled how the narrative was told.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Declassified CIA documents reveal that US officials were highly aware of the
importance that the spread of information had on Argentinian repression.
Videla&#x27;s military regime did not rely upon force alone; it strove to suppress
and eliminate dissident voices using popular media. In one declassified US
document of President Carter&#x27;s report on Argentina, the view of General Ramon
Camps, a senior Argentinian security official, warned that &quot;parents, news,
media, and dissidents were corrupting the minds of young impressionable people&quot;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;santization-and-censorship&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Here, the information itself is framed as a
threat to the public, rather than an asset.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This framing is critical to the successful repression of the Argentinian
people. By portraying journalists and dissidents as ideological enemies under
the same umbrella, the military regime justified censorship in the name of
national security. What&#x27;s alarming is that US officials acknowledged this
reasoning without objection. The document neither challenges the statement made
by Camps, nor does it question the legitimacy of repressing the media. Instead,
Camps&#x27; recount of the justification is given in a neutral, matter-of-fact tone.
This tonality is widespread when reporting on the &quot;Dirty War.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tone and phrasing matters. As reports circulate within the CIA and other
US offices, repression by Videla&#x27;s regime is described as countersubversion,
internal security, or for the benefit of the nation. The extreme acts of
violence, such as forced disappearances, tortures, and extralegal murders, are
acknowledged, but stripped of the emotional impact. This desensitizes and
sanitizes the narrative to minimize the cost of human lives from state violence
while preserving the geopolitical motivations behind it. This framing allowed
US policymakers and officials to tolerate the atrocities in a faraway nation
like Argentina without confronting their moral and ethical implications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The censorship within Argentina and the sanitization within US reporting
reinforced one another. As Argentinian journalists were silenced via
intimidation and violence, American intelligence briefings filled the missing
information with ideological justifications rather than the suppressed voices.
The awareness of Argentinian events remained, but the emotional impact did not.
The choice to minimize the narrative on the regime&#x27;s victims allowed the &quot;Dirty
War&quot; to remain on the periphery of the US public&#x27;s mind, even as evidence
continued to come in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This selective narrative was not accidental. As the previous article stated,
the Cold War ideological tension encouraged the United States to view the mass
oppression in Argentina as a successful suppression of communist ideals. To
further entrench the public in this view, media sanitization was a logical
extension.  In accepting Videla&#x27;s perspective of leftist ideology as
terroristic and violence as necessary, US officials contributed to an
environment where state terror and internal persecution were normalized and
commonplace.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Narrative controls how we understand, remember, respond, and take
responsibility for events. The next article will examine how this narrative
translates to the memory and legacy of the &quot;Dirty War.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#bibliography&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reaganlibrary.gov&#x2F;public&#x2F;digitallibrary&#x2F;argentina&#x2F;argentina-carterreports.pdf&quot;&gt;Carter Report&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>America&#x27;s Battleground | The Cold War Sacrifice of Argentina</title>
        <published>2026-01-23T21:30:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-23T21:30:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Brodin Faser
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/cold-war-ideology/"/>
        <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/cold-war-ideology/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/cold-war-ideology/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;america-s-battleground-the-cold-war-sacrifice-of-argentina&quot;&gt;America&#x27;s Battleground | The Cold War Sacrifice of Argentina&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#america-s-battleground-the-cold-war-sacrifice-of-argentina&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Dirty War&quot; occurred during the height of the Cold War. In this context,
Argentina was allowed to devolve into chaos because the ideals of the military
dictatorship aligned with the United States&#x27; political agenda.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-article&quot;&gt;The Article&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#the-article&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first article in this series establishes that the US knew about Argentina&#x27;s
political environment and the inevitability of a military takeover, a coup
d&#x27;état. US agents were already monitoring guerrilla activities and the steady
increase in anti-leftist efforts. However, the US awareness of the upcoming
coup does not explain the lack of meaningful intervention. To do so, the &quot;Dirty
War&quot; must be considered in the broader geopolitical context of the Cold War.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was the Cold War? Some of us remember it as our childhood, so I do not
need to define it here; you lived through it. Nevertheless, I will give a brief
overview for those unfamiliar. The Cold War was an indirect ideological
conflict between the United States&#x27; capitalism and the Soviet Union&#x27;s
communism. US foreign policy during this period was less about promoting
democratic and capitalist views and more about containing and eradicating
communist ones &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;cold-war-ideology&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Why is Argentina important in this context? It is
because the &quot;Dirty War&quot; was a metaphorical proving ground for these conflicting
ideals. In addition, the US viewed political instability as a threat to
capitalism, where communism could take hold. For this reason, right-wing
authoritarian regimes, like the one during the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; promised control
and security against the communist ideals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Argentina&#x27;s political crisis unfolded within this framework. After the military
coup in March 1976, the country came under a military dictatorship led by
General Jorge Rafael Videla. To Videla, the road to restoring national unity
came through repression and fear. Under Videla, forced disappearances, torture
one beyond recognition, and extrajudicial murders were justified as measures
against leftist subversion. These actions, blatant human rights violations,
were both common and conspicuous to the public &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;cold-war-ideology&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Recently
declassified US documents reveal that the Americans were aware of the methods
employed by Videla and his regime as well as his justification for these
actions. While political violence contributed to the instability of Argentina
before the coup, it was later used &quot;as a rationale for a no-holds-barred
approach to counter-terrorism,&quot; resulting in &quot;egregious violations of human
rights, despite public recognition by the government that the terrorists have
been largely defeated&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;cold-war-ideology&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. While the US officials recognized the
severity of the actions that occurred under Videla, there was no action to
remedy this situation. This reflected the political agenda of the US, where
security against communism was more important than preserving human rights in a
foreign nation. Even in the quote above, the issue is framed in terms of the
counterterrorism movement against leftist sentiments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This declassified document and the resulting analysis reveal how the US&#x27; Cold
War priorities twisted the perception of Argentinian violence under Videla&#x27;s
dictatorship. For the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; awareness did not lead to intervention;
instead, brutality and human rights concerns were swept under the rug in favor
of an ideological defense against communism. Argentina became the battleground
of Cold War ideologies not because the US intervened, but because they did
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The US allowed Argentina to devolve into chaos, where terror and torture
were not just permissible but commonplace, all for their own political and
ideological agenda.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#bibliography&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.britannica.com&#x2F;event&#x2F;Cold-War&quot;&gt;Cold War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ebookcentral.proquest.com&#x2F;lib&#x2F;whitworth&#x2F;detail.action?docID=1211193&quot;&gt;State Terrorism in Latin America: Chile, Argentina, and International Human Rights&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reaganlibrary.gov&#x2F;public&#x2F;digitallibrary&#x2F;argentina&#x2F;argentina-carterreports.pdf&quot;&gt;Carter Report&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>American Action -and Inaction- before Argentina&#x27;s Coup d&#x27;État</title>
        <published>2026-01-23T21:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-23T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Brodin Faser
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/american-inaction/"/>
        <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/american-inaction/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/american-inaction/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;american-action-and-inaction-before-argentina-s-coup-d-etat&quot;&gt;American Action -and Inaction- before Argentina&#x27;s Coup d&#x27;État&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#american-action-and-inaction-before-argentina-s-coup-d-etat&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US knew about the political crisis unfolding in Argentina prior to the
&quot;Dirty War&quot;, where violence and human rights violations started to become
widespread. Despite this, they refused to offer aid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-article&quot;&gt;The Article&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#the-article&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leading up to the military coup d&#x27;état that ushered in Argentina&#x27;s &quot;Dirty War&quot;,
the country dealt with significant political instability. From 1930 to 1976
(the beginning of the &quot;Dirty War&quot;), Argentina experienced roughly 9 coups and
more than 20 different political leaders &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;american-inaction&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. During this, leftist
groups were banding together for guerrilla warfare. These guerrilla groups
robbed and stole &quot;Robin Hood-style&quot;, stealing from the rich and giving to the
poor &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;american-inaction&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. By the 1970s, Argentina&#x27;s instability-shaped by lingering
World War II ideologies and intensifying Cold War tensions-caught the attention
of the United States.  In fact, the US had already stationed intelligence
operatives throughout Argentina, monitoring the political climate. On July 2,
1975, US officials in Argentina reported terrorist plans from the Argentine
People&#x27;s Revolutionary Army (ERP), one of the guerrilla groups mentioned
earlier. They reported concerns that the ERP planned to kidnap US officials and
attack their embassy in Buenos Aires &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;american-inaction&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. While
they only reported concerns for the US officials, it highlights Argentina&#x27;s
rising instability and the US&#x27; awareness of it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another declassified document, the US discussed the persecution of leftist
groups throughout Latin America. The report starts with the statement about the
political atmosphere, commenting on the known violation of human rights
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;american-inaction&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This shows that the US fully knew of the things
occurring in Argentina.  Following this, the focus shifts to Argentina&#x27;s
&quot;legal&quot; persecution of leftist sympathizers.  The document hints that the
government was overturning exiles in favor of execution, outside the law. These
points emphasize the instability of Latin America as a whole, with Argentina
leading the charge &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;american-inaction&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. It shows that the US knew of
the war crimes and inhumane actions that culminated in the &quot;Dirty War.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these documents show that the US was not a bystander in Argentina&#x27;s
political collapse, but an observer with a clear view of the nation&#x27;s descent
into violence. The US intelligence agents documented the guerrilla activity,
predicted the military repression, and acknowledged the rising political
persecution of the left. Despite this, they decided neither to intervene nor
offer aid. The US minimized the suffering of the Argentinian people, shown by
the nonchalant mentions of the human rights abuses. As the tensions of the Cold
War escalated, the situation in Argentina was seen not as a humanitarian crisis
but as a strategic battle for ideological supremacy. By choosing to observe
rather than intervene, the United States facilitated the conditions necessary
for repression to spread unchecked. In the next article, we will explore how
the Cold War and the US&#x27; tactical agenda made the refusal of aid not just
acceptable but politically advantageous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#bibliography&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ebookcentral.proquest.com&#x2F;lib&#x2F;whitworth&#x2F;detail.action?docID=1211193&quot;&gt;State Terrorism in Latin America: Chile, Argentina, and International Human Rights&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cia.gov&#x2F;readingroom&#x2F;docs&#x2F;MEETING%20OF%20LEFTIST%20TERROR%5B15518274%5D.pdf&quot;&gt;Meeting of Leftist Terrorists in Argentina&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.cia.gov&#x2F;readingroom&#x2F;docs&#x2F;NATIONAL%20INTELLIGENCE%20DAI%5B15499914%5D.pdf&quot;&gt;National Intelligence Daily&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Argentina&#x27;s Dirty War</title>
        <published>2026-01-13T21:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-13T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Brodin Faser
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/dirty-war/"/>
        <id>https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/dirty-war/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://bfaser.github.io/WL-261-Project/posts/dirty-war/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;argentina-s-dirty-war&quot;&gt;Argentina&#x27;s &quot;Dirty War&quot;&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#argentina-s-dirty-war&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Dirty War&quot; is the period between 1976 and 1983 when Argentina was ruled by
an authoritarian military dictatorship. The term &quot;Dirty War,&quot; Guerra Sucia in
Spanish, describing this period in Argentinian history is often rejected by
human rights groups today, as it implies the notion of justified and
necessitated action amid war. This implication, that war was underway in
Argentina, is entirely false; The &quot;Dirty War&quot; describes the systematic
persecution of Argentinian citizens by their own government, using unlawful and
cruel methods. General Rafael Videla, the dictator during the &quot;Dirty War,&quot;
persecuted his own people using terrorist tactics including abduction, torture,
and murder. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1,5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Even today, the effects of this period
can be felt. Very little literature and evidence exist today from this period
because of the fearmongering and censorship enacted by the Argentinian
leadership &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. While many of the primary perpetrators of this
horrific event have been tried under the current Argentinian judicial system,
many still feel that proper justice has not been served. As Sam Furguson writes
in his book The Disappeared: Remnants of a Dirty War, &quot;But the trial is as much
about the &#x27;symbols of the dictatorship&#x27; who created an &#x27;Argentine Auschwitz&#x27; as
it is about the individual crimes enumerated in the charging papers&quot; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 50 years leading up to the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; Argentina experienced nine
military coups and the oversight of more than twenty different political
leaders between 1930 and 1976 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This period of substantial
political instability spans all of World War II and extends into a significant
portion of the Cold War. While Argentina remained neutral throughout the
majority of WWII, it was the location of refuge for many sympathizers of Nazi
Germany. These refugees brought with them anti-Semitic sentiments, further
contributing to Argentina&#x27;s instability. In the aftermath of World War II, the
Cold War arose between the United States and the Soviet Union. The primary
cause for this conflict was the ideological incompatibility between the Soviet
communism and the American capitalism &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In this context, Argentina
was used as a proving ground for these competing ideas.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 1975, a proposition was passed under the guise of opposing the
leftist guerrilla threat, directing the military to eradicate &quot;subversion&quot;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. With this proposition, the military expanded its anti-leftist
efforts to the point of terrorism. These actions were conducted to eliminate
anti-capitalist ideals that had been circulating and had caused the initial
guerrilla attacks. Contributing to this hostile and tumultuous environment were
the remnants of World War II ideals. Argentina harbored a vast number of Jews
who immigrated over the century leading up to the outbreak of the &quot;Dirty War.&quot;
Following the conclusion of WWII, sympathizers of Nazi Germany brought with
them their anti-Semitic sentiments that resonated with the extreme right-wing.
This religious tension and continuation of World War II ideological differences
led to the Jews and leftists being scapegoats for any problem Argentina faced
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In this light, Jacobo Timerman, a prisoner of the Argentinian
dictatorship, summarized the mindset of the leadership as the following: &quot;World
War III had begun; the enemy was left-wing terrorism; and Argentina was the
initial battleground chosen by the enemy.&quot; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the military takeover that ushered in the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; political
instability in Argentina reached a breaking point as leftist groups conducted
guerrilla attacks across the country. These leftist warriors attacked &quot;Robin
Hood-style,&quot; stealing food and other necessities to distribute in impoverished
areas in hopes of raising public support &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Nearing 1970, the
attacks from the left became directed towards military personnel and
right-leaning politicians. Fearing another world war, José López Rega though
the Argentinian president at the time, Juan D. Perón, formed the Alianza
Anticommunista Argentina (or Argentine Anticommunist Alliance, AAA) to
neutralize the leftist action &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. The AAA was a &quot;death squad&quot;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; sanctioned by the president to eliminate the leftist
insurrectionists, or anyone harboring ideology different than capitalism. It
also laid the foundation for the &quot;Dirty War,&quot; as the violence sharply increase
in the year following. In July 1974, the AAA drastically increased its activity
and ferocity against the left&#x27;s terrorism following Perón&#x27;s death. As a result,
support for the Argentinian leadership dwindled until the military coup d&#x27;état
on March 24, 1976 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This military coup on March 24, considered necessary due to the excessive AAA
violence and their terroristic methods, sought to restore order and structure
to Argentina. The first program proposed to remedy the situation Argentina
faced was El Processo de Reorgananización Nacional (The Process of National
Reorganization) &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. It proposed the swift and decisive
eradication of those opposing the new leadership, so that order could be
reinstated. With this, the Argentinian military had complete control over the
nation and all its inhabitants &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Within months, the military
dictatorship was persecuting and heavily suppressing the Argentinian public.
The approach was order through overwhelming terror, where no one would dare
oppose the leadership. In a speech to the public, the figurehead of the
dictatorship, Rafael Videla, spoke on imposing justice and reaffirming liberty.
Taken in conjunction with his speech months earlier where he expressed his
willingness to protect the nation no matter the cost, Videla forbode a grim and
bloody future to come &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. With this, Videla ushered in the
&quot;Dirty War&quot; of Argentina.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Dirty War&quot; was characterized by the Argentinian dictatorship using state
terror to suppress political dissidence and maintain control. Instead of solely
relying upon legal measures for unifying the nation, the military dictatorship
chose to make use of extralegal, clandestine repression. As Thomas C. Wright
explains, the leadership justified its actions as necessary to combat the
subversion from the left. This justification enabled the dictatorship to commit
numerous human rights violations, including but not limited to abductions,
torture, and murder &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This violence was used to intimidate the
Argentinian people into submission and eliminate any semblance of political
opposition.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One extralegal repression tactic used by the military dictatorship extensively
during the &quot;Dirty War&quot; to rid the nation of any perceived threats was forced
disappearance. These forced disappearances include the kidnapping, exile, and
murder of Argentinian citizens. Tens of thousands of Argentinians were abducted
by the military, with 62% happening in the dead of night and witnessed by
another. There was nothing secretive about these disappearances. In fact, the
Argentinian officials would deliberately call attention to themselves to
amplify the terror felt by those nearby &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Once abducted, the
victims were taken to the Argentinian equivalent of concentration camps, the
location of which was and still is unknown. These camps were deliberately
concealed to further enhance the fear felt by neighbors and loved ones, who had
no way of knowing whether the individual was alive &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. An estimated
380 of these concentration camps were scattered throughout Argentina, sometimes
in plain sight. As former prisoner recounts, &quot;I could hear people walking by
cars and buses passing, life going on as usual, with us disappeared in a
concentration camp. We were in the world but not part of it, alive in the realm
of death&quot; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dictatorship would justify these actions as only occurring to leftist
dissidents and threats to the stability of Argentina, although the definition
of &quot;leftist dissident&quot; had expanded throughout the &quot;Dirty War.&quot;  Students,
journalists, intellectuals, and anyone suspected of harboring dissident
intentions was now included under the umbrella of &quot;left dissidence&quot;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Marguerite Feitlowitz emphasizes that language itself was a
tool of repression used by the military, using euphemisms and other verbiage to
obscure their actions and further dehumanize the victims &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.
These atrocities were permissible under the authoritarian regime of military
dictatorship, as the definition of &quot;subversive action&quot; was vague. This
manipulation of the definition facilitated and normalized the violence
committed by the military.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond physical means of controlling and suppressing the Argentinian
population, the military regime made extensive use of fear. Sam Ferguson
describes the universal presence of forced disappearance altering the social
atmosphere, seeding distrust within communities, and encouraging silence and
self-censorship for fear of being another victim &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. The military
dictatorship was able to easily maintain extreme level of fear and terrorism
because the Argentinian people were self-policing and self-censoring, too
afraid of becoming next among the disappeared.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects of these atrocities can be felt today and shape the narrative
around Argentinian history. Although democracy was instated in 1983 and many of
the state-sanctioned terrorists persecuted, there are lingering questions of
proper justice, accountability, and remembrance. Brennan remarks that the
absence of physical evidence and trauma inflicted upon the surviving victims
complicates the recovery from this event, both nationally and individually
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bfaser.github.io&#x2F;WL-261-Project&#x2F;posts&#x2F;dirty-war&#x2F;#bibliography&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Acknowledging the mechanisms by which the Argentinian
military was able to instate petrifying fear on a national level, as well as
the consequences of the extreme oppression felt by the Argentinian people, is
essential to understanding Argentinian history and recognizing the long-term
effects of state-sponsored terrorism on a society.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;a class=&quot;anchor&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;#bibliography&quot; hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1525&#x2F;california&#x2F;9780520297913.001.0001&quot;&gt;Argentina’s Missing Bones: Revisiting the History of the Dirty War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.britannica.com&#x2F;event&#x2F;Cold-War&quot;&gt;Cold War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ebookcentral.proquest.com&#x2F;lib&#x2F;whitworth&#x2F;detail.action?docID=5824898&quot;&gt;A Lexicon of Terror: Argentina and the Legacies of Torture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ebookcentral.proquest.com&#x2F;lib&#x2F;whitworth&#x2F;detail.action?docID=30585644&quot;&gt;The Disappeared: Remnants of a Dirty War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ebookcentral.proquest.com&#x2F;lib&#x2F;whitworth&#x2F;detail.action?docID=1211193&quot;&gt;State Terrorism in Latin America: Chile, Argentina, and International Human Rights&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
